Guide to the Paul Kwilecki Photographs and Papers, 1960-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographic Materials Series, 1960-2001 (bulk 1970s-1990s) and undated
  - Oversize Material Subseries
    - Decatur County Court House Oversize Prints
      - 1981 Dec., 142-1281-8 (Oversize-box 1)
        This prisoner from the County Farm restored and refinished this light fixture which originally hung in the court room. Initially it was a gas fixture, later converted to electricity. The brass had been painted over several times and the whole thing was about to be thrown out.
      - A family anxiously waits outside court room, 1980 Apr. (Understandings), 42-480-5 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Prisoners over steaming vat, 1983 Mar., 12-383-14 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Hog killing at the County Farm, 1983 Mar., 14-383-13 (Oversize-box 1)
        Early morning and very cold.
      - 1983 Mar., 13-383-11 (Oversize-box 1)
        These hogs are about to be dipped in the vat of hot water.
      - Butchering hogs at the county farm, 1983 Mar., 12-383-9 (Oversize-box 1)
        This ritual goes on throughout the county at this time of year.
      - Prisoners at the county farm killing hogs, 1983 Mar., 13-383-34 (Oversize-box 1)
        It was a bitterly cold, windy day. This man is removing the brain and tongue from the head of the hog.
      - Butchering hogs, County Farm (prison), 1983 Mar., 13-383-4 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Cemetery Cleaning: Greenshade Cemetery, Oversize Prints
      - Text: Cemetery Cleaning/Greenshade Cemetery, 1977 Apr. (Oversize-box 1)
        This text gives a brief description of Greenshade Cemetery and describes a work day and picnic that took place at the cemetery Apr. 30, 1977.
    - Battle's Quarters Oversize Prints
      - Man in doorway, baby on porch floor, circa 1971 [matted], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        I have observed elsewhere that life in the quarters was lived mostly out of doors. To demonstrate how true that is, this man was making love to a woman just inside the open door when he saw me about to photograph his child on the porch. He is in the process of dressing himself as he looks dauntingly at me.
      - Two men and women seated, 1970 [matted], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        Saturday afternoon and everyone sits around in the shade and talks. These three were totally unconcerned with my photography. I had to interrupt them to ask them to look my way.
    - Bainbridge, Georgia Oversize Prints
      - Short order restaurant on North Broad Street at night, 1970 [matted], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
      - Broad Street on Sunday morning, 1980 June, 62-680-22 (Oversize-box 1)
      - North Broad Street, 1980 Aug. (Understandings), 82-880-10 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Interior of pool hall on North Broad Street owned and operated by Ertha Lee Coney, 1981 Apr., 45-481-8 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Flint River, Oversize Prints
      - A family and their vehicle picnicking by the river, 1979 May, 68-579 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Runner warming up before race at springtime festival, 1978 Apr., 37-578-24a (Oversize-box 1)
      - A yearly festival used to be held on the banks of the Flint to celebrate spring, 1980 May, 54-580-15 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Man, baby, wife with inner tube at Boat Basin Beach, 1981 May, 77-581-7 (Oversize-box 1)
      - Boys under sign at Boat Basin Beach, 1981 June, 81-681-11 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Houses, Oversize Prints
      - 1965. Beecher Thomas and wife in living room. [matted], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        Interior of the home of Mr. and Mrs. Beecher Thomas on Shotwell and Scott Streets.
      - Interior of Gus Poulas residence, circa 1969 [matted], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        This boy rented a room from Gus. This photograph was purchased by the Museum of Modern Art many years ago.
    - Portraits
      - Dr. Ehrlich in his treatment room, 1975 [mounted on board], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        Dr. M. A. Ehrlich in his operating room on his 75th birthday. He and his brother had this small downtown clinic years ago. As I took his picture he reminisced about times gone by. See my notes for more on this.
      - Woman sitting in window in burned house, circa 1963 [mounted on board], unnumbered (Oversize-box 1)
        This was an early effort, not fully successful but not altogether a failure either.
    - Religion, Oversize Prints
      - Preacher standing by poster, [circa 1965], 2; unnumbered (Oversize-box 2)
        This preacher is standing in the anteroom of his small church. Once I didn't like this picture. Now I do.
      - Rev. Mitchell preaching prior to baptizing in Mt. Zuma's brand new pool, 1982 Apr., 38-482-9a (Oversize-box 2)
      - Rev. Mitchell preaching to the children before baptism, 1982 Apr., 36-482-16 (Oversize-box 2)
      - First baptism in Mt. Zuma's new pool behind church, 1982 Apr., 38-482-14a (Oversize-box 2)
        Rev. Mitchell, left; Ben Edwards, right.
      - Sunday morning church service. Camilla, Ga., 1984 Jan., 2-84-26 (Oversize-box 2)
    - Shoppers, Oversize Prints
      - Women talking in grocery store, 1977 Aug., 96-877-15a (Oversize-box 2)
      - Women loading groceries in their car, 1977 Apr., 16-477-11 (Oversize-box 2)
        Typical supermarket entrance.
    - Stores, Oversize Prints
      - Woman and baby in laundromat in Bainbridge Mall, 1973, unnumbered (Oversize-box 2)
    - Swine Time, Oversize Prints
      - Husband and wife, 1974, unnumbered (Oversize-box 2)
    - Workers, Oversize Prints
      - Stoker at Elberta Crate Co., circa 1970, unnumbered (Oversize-box 2)
        This man stoked the boilers at Elberta Crate Co. back in the days when boilers were stoked. Refreshingly, he is the opposite of cosmetic. Real.
      - Elberta Crate Co., 1981 Dec., 147-1281-10 (Oversize-box 2)
      - Horace Battles at Elberta Crate Co., 1981 Dec., 141-1281-3 (Oversize-box 2)
        He managed the boilers and blew the whistle. See my notes for more details.
      - Loggers in the woods near Attapulgus, 1978 Feb., 19-278-12 (Oversize-box 2)
    - Additional Oversize Material
      - Cape Cod, Photographs by David Vestal, Quadrant Prints [in large paper portfolio], [1960s?], (6 prints, some age damage) (Oversize-box 2)
- Contact Sheets, 1979-1990 and undated, (19 boxes)
  Contains Kwilecki's contact sheets, received after his death and arranged in original order as found in his house and studio. Boxes PHO 11-PHO 20 were housed in original Box 18, and are labeled with dates from 1980 to 1983, and some are undated. Boxes PHO 21-PHO 30 were originally housed in Box 21, and are labeled with dates from 1979 to 1990, and undated.
  - Addition 2010-0126 (Box PHO 11-PHO 30)
- Negatives, undated (RESTRICTED), (6 boxes)
  Boxes NEG 1-NEG 3, large records storage cartons, are marked as "House Negatives"; Box NEG 4 is marked as "Office Negatives." Boxes NEG 5-NEG 6 were originally housed in Box 21.
  [Access to original negatives is restricted: whenever possible, prints are to be used for image access. Currently unarranged and undated.]
  - Addition 2010-0126 (Box NEG 1-NEG 6)
- Manuscripts Series, 1966-2008 and undated
  [Kwilecki's personal journals in this series are closed to use until 2017.]
  This series includes correspondence and journals, the largest and most extensive groupings, as well as biographical materials, writing and speeches, and printed material. Boxes 1 and 2 are arranged into the following categories: Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Printed Material and Journals. Within each category, folders are arranged chronologically. Box 1 contains a brief biography of Kwilecki, correspondence related to Kwilecki's photography, printing notes for Kwilecki's prints, exhibition brochures, news clippings, customer receipts. It also contains an interview given to P.J. Brownlee in which Kwilecki speaks of Decatur County, his philosophy and method of photography, technical aspects of photography, and individual series and prints. Also included are speeches given by Kwilecki which relate to his publishing experience, his philosophy of photography, his love for Decatur County, and his experiences as a self-taught documentary photographer. Finally, Box MSS 1 includes Kwilecki's writings on the following subjects and photograph series: the Decatur County Court House, Shade Tobacco, Tobacco Residue, Battle's Quarters, The Soldier in Willis Park, Stores, The Trailways Bus Station, the Flint River, Houses, Decatur County Newspapers, Cemeteries, Inhabitants of Decatur County, Decatur County Farms, Factory Workers, Religion, Jr./Sr. Prom, and Hog Killing.
  Box MSS 2 contains Kwilecki's journals [closed to use until 2017] dating from 1967 to 1969, in which he writes on photography, his life as a documentary photographer, and personal issues.
  Additional minimally-processed personal papers from addition 2010-0126 (13 boxes) contain correspondence and other files, and are described below.
  - Biographical Data Subseries (Box MSS 1)
    - Biography Resource Center Biography of Kwilecki, undated (Box MSS 1)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1966 June-1992 Apr. and undated, (8 folders) (Box MSS 1)
  - Writings and Speeches Subseries, 1977-2001 and undated, (4 folders)
    - Kwilecki interview conducted by P.J. Brownlee, 1994 Dec. 28 (Box MSS 1)
    - Restoring the Decatur County Courthouse, 1998-2000, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - La Grange talk, 1999 Feb. 17 (Box MSS 1)
    - Hog Killing at the County Farm, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Duke lecture, 2001 Oct. 3, (2 copies) (Box MSS 1)
    - The Junior-Senior Prom, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Society for Photographic Education Talk, 1994 Nov. 5 (Box MSS 1)
      Given by Kwilecki to the Society for Photographic Education in Atlanta, Ga.
    - My Publishing Experience, 1994 Apr. 30 (Box MSS 1)
      Given by Kwilecki at the High Museum of Art in Atlanta, Ga.
    - Gallery Talk, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Collection of Kwilecki's writings on Decatur County people, places, things and events, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Printing notes, 1977-1991 (Box MSS 1)
  - Printed Material Subseries, 1970-2001 and undated, (3 folders)
    - Customer receipts, undated, (2 receipts) (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Barbara Morgan exhibition of photography, The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1972 Mar. 8-May 31 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Discovery: Inner and Outer Worlds, Portfolio II, The Friends of Photography, Carmel, California, 1970 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Introducing Fine Photographs, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - News clipping regarding Kwilecki's exhibit, Decatur County Georgia, being shown at Duke University, 2001 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Paul Kwilecki: Decatur County, Georgia, 1994 Nov. 4-Dec. 21 (Box MSS 1)
      This exhibit was shown at Lehigh University.
    - News article honoring Kwilecki for his gift of 12 courthouse photographs to Decatur county, undated, (photocopy) (Box MSS 1)
    - A Decatur County Resolution honoring Kwilecki for his gift of photography, undated, (photocopy) (Box MSS 1)
    - Information regarding Kwilecki's traveling exhibit, Homage: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia, 1997 and undated (Box MSS 1)
  - Journals Subseries, 1967 Mar. 30-1969 Oct. 14 [CLOSED until 2017], (8 folders) (Box MSS 2)
  - Addition (2010-0126), 1971-2008 and undated, (14 boxes)
    Received following Paul Kwilecki's passing, this addition to the collection contains his personal papers, a arranged largely in the original folder order. Boxes MSS 3-10 are arranged alphabetically by the original folder title and include correspondence to individuals, organizations, and letters to Kwilecki. Boxes MSS 11-12 contain Kwilecki's correspondence from 1972-1983, 1992-1993 and 1995, arranged chronologically by original folder title. Box MSS 13 contains Kwilecki's correspondence with photographers David Vestal and Alex Harris. Boxes MSS 14-15 house writings, clippings, and other items. Box MSS 16 contains five publications and several folders of papers: a mix of personal exchanges with family (one folder), dating from 1971-2008 (bulk 1980s-1990s); notes for a book on Decatur County photographs (one folder); paper copies of scans and correspondence with Tom Rankin about a book (2008) (three folders); and another folder of writings (drafts of lectures and talks, and journalistic entries dating from the 1970s). There are also two video cassettes of interviews with Kwilecki.
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Correspondence Files (Box MSS 3-13)
    - Additional Correspondence, Publicity, and Writings Files, 1971-2008 and undated (Box MSS 14-16)
    - Publications (Box MSS 16)
      - Understandings: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia. Paul Kwilecki. Introduction by Alex Harris. Center for Documentary Photography: University of N.C. at Chapel Hill, NC, 1981 (inscribed with Jane Kwilecki's name) (Box MSS 16)
      - Photographs by Paul Kwilecki. High Museum of Art [Atlanta] Calendar of Events, 1980 Dec. (Box MSS 16)
      - The Land's People. Paul Kwilecki. American Land Forum, Volume V, No. 1, Winter 1985 (Box MSS 16)
      - Workers of Decatur County, Georgia. Paul Kwilecki. Southern Quarterly, Spring 1994 (Box MSS 16)
      - Homage: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia. Essay by Paul Kwilecki for large-format brochure. Winthrop University galleries, South Carolina State Museum exhibits, 1997 (Box MSS 16)
    - Videocassettes, (2 VHS cassettes) (Box MSS 16)
    - Publicity poster for Scenes from Decatur County exhibit, Hartford, Conn., 2002 (signed by Kwilecki), (2 copies) (Opaperfolder 1)